When analyzing both discrete and continuous quantitative data,
عند تحليل كل من البيانات الكمية المنفصلة والكمية المستمرة،
we generally discuss four main aspects.
نناقش بشكل عام أربعة جوانب رئيسية.
The center, the spread,
المركز والانتشار
the shape and outliers.
والشكل والقيم المتطرفة.
In this lesson, we will focus on measures of center.
في هذا الدرس، سنركز على مقاييس المركز.
There are three widely accepted measures of center.
هناك ثلاثة مقاييس مقبولة على نطاق واسع من المركز.
The mean, the median and the mode.
المتوسط والوسيط والوضع.
To illustrate how each of these measures is calculated,
لتوضيح كيفية حساب كل من هذه المقاييس،
consider this table of the number of dogs I see at the coffee shop in a week.
ضع في اعتبارك هذا الجدول الذي يوضح عدد الكلاب التي أراها في المقهى في غضون أسبوع.
From the table, we can see that on Monday, I saw five dogs.
من الجدول، يمكننا أن نرى أنه في يوم الاثنين، رأيت خمسة كلاب.
On Tuesday, I saw three dogs.
وفي يوم الثلاثاء، رأيت ثلاثة كلاب.
On Wednesday, I saw eight dogs and so on.
وفي يوم الأربعاء، رأيت ثمانية كلاب وهكذا.
A friend might ask you,
قد يسألك أحد الأصدقاء،
how many dogs would you expect to see on any given day?
كم عدد الكلاب التي تتوقع أن تراها في أي يوم من الأيام؟
We might choose to respond to this in a lot of different ways.
قد نختار الرد على ذلك بطرق مختلفة.
Like, it depends on the day or it depends on the week.
مثل، ذلك يعتمد على اليوم أو يعتمد على الأسبوع.
But commonly, the word expect is associated with the mean or the average of our data set.
ولكن عادةً ما تكون كلمة "توقع" مرتبطة بوسيط أو متوسط مجموعة بياناتنا.
The mean is calculated as the sum of all of
يتم حساب الوسيط كمجموع لجميع
the values in our data set divided by how many data points we have.
القيم في مجموعة البيانات مقسومًا على عدد نقاط البيانات المتوفرة لدينا.
As you can see calculated here,
كما ترى محسوبًا هنا،
this value is 12.57 dogs.
هذه القيمة هي 12.57 كلبًا.
That is, the sum of the number of dogs observed on
أي مجموع عدد الكلاب التي تتم ملاحظتها في
each day divided by the number of days in a week.
كل يوم مقسومًا على عدد الأيام في الأسبوع.
The mean isn't always the best measure of center.
الوسيط ليس دائمًا أفضل مقياس للمركز.
For this data set,
بالنسبة لمجموعة البيانات هذه،
you can see that the mean doesn't really seem like it's in the middle of the data at all.
يمكنك أن ترى أن الوسيط لا يبدو في الواقع أنه في وسط البيانات على الإطلاق.
There are only two of the seven days that have recorded more dogs than the reported mean.
لا يوجد سوى اثنين من الأيام السبعة التي سجلت كلاب أكثر من المتوسط المبلغ عنه.
It also is splitting our dogs into
كما أنها تقسم كلابنا إلى
decimal values which will seem strange when we're reporting back to our friend.
قيم عشرية ستبدو غريبة عندما نبلغ صديقنا.